All right.
In this lecture
we're going to talk about distributed
file systems in multi hybrid
cloud environments.
A distributed file
system has been around for a while.
Primarily started in, grid computing
back in the late 90s, early 2000.
Mostly to handle massively parallel jobs.
But there's a lot of benefits
to distributed file systems
in cloud computing
and in multi, hybrid cloud.
One of the cool things about it
is that I can scale storage
beyond beyond a single device.
There's lots of commercial opportunities
for this that are out there.
Both software based
and also even some hardware
based, distributed file systems
that are out there.
It can achieve really high
availability and fault tolerance,
and it can enable seamless sharding
or sharing of of data across
distributed teams environments,
which is why it came, you know,
a lot of out of the high performance
computing or great computing space.
Okay, the basic structure of this
is that you've got storage nodes
and you've got a metadata server.
The metadata server keeps
track of where things are
in your distributed file system across
all the different storage nodes,
which could be, on different,
physical, locations,
on different clouds
or whatever the case may be.
So now when a client comes and talks
to something,
it hits the meta server,
metadata server first,
then establishes the connection
to where the storage actually is.
And then you can get the information
from there.
Any time I store new information
to these storage nodes,
the metadata server is updated so
everything hits the metadata server first.
And then the the appropriate
file is brought back to you.
You think there's a lot of overhead
in this hand?
There was at first.
But like I said before,
there are some hardware acceleration,
that actually can speed
some of this stuff up quite a bit.
Right.
And those are available
as commercial products and also open
source products can take advantage
of some new silicon features
that can speed some of this stuff up.
So core characteristics,
distributed file systems,
transparency,
meaning location and access transparency.
They hide all that complexity
away from the user.
So the user just accesses a file system
and they have no idea
where the data is actually coming from.
Right.
So this gives me the ability to scale.
I can add more storage
or I can add more access points.
Some of the newer things like vast
data is a great example of this.
They can scale the storage and the,
the access,
throughput independent of each other
by act
adding more access
nodes, to the storage underneath.
It provides a great fault tolerance
and replication across multiple nodes.
So if you have one server that goes down,
and I've got a replica of maybe three,
in a storage array of,
six,
that means I can get all the way down to,
two servers and still be running
without a problem, right?
Not as fast, probably, but all the data
has been replicated,
across, across those,
servers.
And you can set up your replication
policies and all that stuff.
Security is kind of built in with secure
for our fine grained security and access
control based off of traditional Unix,
security, mechanisms.
But they can also tie in to any,
IAM system
that's out there today.
All right.
So here are some common,
distributed file system architectures.
One is the client server model.
A great example of this is in NFS and AFS,
where I've got a central metadata server
that manages the directory hierarchy.
So the problem with this possibly
is a single point of failure, right?
Now a lot of times
they'll put that meta, metadata server,
on, multiple nodes, which they can do.
But it,
it increases the complexity of things
standard and out of the box,
it tends to run on one node.
So if that one node goes down,
you're kind of hosed
the other.
Or more like decentralized models
like self and IPFs,
where metadata and data are distributed
across all the nodes.
So it automatically built into resiliency
there.
There's other ones in there.
Popular DFS examples like HDFs,
self cluster fs, I use that one.
Minio is another one,
that uses a distributed
file system type, but it's more object
based and file system based.
Right.
And then cloud manage
I've got Amazon EFS and Azure files
which are opportunities for this.
But the same architectural concepts exist
in both object
storage distributed object storage. And
and a distributed file system,
that are out there.
So here's
a great example of a decentralized versus
a client server.
Distributed file system decentralized.
As I said before, each node contains
metadata and storage
and may have part parts of that,
metadata.
It uses more like a pub sub hub.
So I'm sending information
to a message bus
that then the different nodes will pick up
and say, I can handle that one.
And typically with a decentralized,
you're going to
still have replicas of your metadata
and your storage.
Right? Where I do, pure client server.
I now have a meta, a metadata server
that could be replicated, but
typically for, simple,
deployments, it's it's not,
but I could replicate it,
put it behind an API gateway.
So now it will hit that metadata server
that will then in turn,
connect you to the right storage node,
and then you're off to the races.
Right.
So there's the difference between the two.
More modern ones are using more
decentralized approach as they're
they,
tend to be easier
to manage and set up right nowadays.
They weren't at first,
but nowadays they're much easier to
to manage and set up.
Then.
Your typical NFS or a client server
based,
systems.
All right.
Let's look at in a multi hybrid
cloud context.
Now it's really important to remember
with multi hybrid cloud
cost ends up being an important aspect.
And so does latency as you're connecting
across multiple clouds.
And sometimes you can hit
into some latency problems.
And if you're moving data out of a cloud
you get the cost of egress
which you have to worry about.
Right.
But this could provide you
a really interesting unified file access
across multiple clouds.
If you're not really worried
about egress costs and you don't want to
fine tune control that, then
this could be a really good way to go.
It can support local,
data, local, locality really easily.
Right.
And if you're using,
some of the more modern ones like
Hammer Space or Macromedia, right.
They actually have policies built in.
So, it will actually help you,
when you're connecting to something
so that you're not moving data
between the clouds,
but that you're actually connecting to
where the data is closest to you
and where it decreases the amount of data.
Boom. Moving out of the cloud. Right.
So data locality is important for fault
tolerance across
multiple clouds would be great.
And then also you can enforce regulatory
compliance with some of these new
newer distributed file systems
that are out there.
Some of the challenges, is synchronizing
data across the clouds
and with different latencies
and your egress costs
huge, huge, huge, huge.
So you gotta watch out for that, right?
Performance obviously can be an issue
if I'm moving across multiple clouds
and you might have some network
constraints in handling
bandwidth limitations between clouds
and data centers and things like that.
Also, if you are using multiple clouds,
or cloud service providers,
you've got to handle identity
across those cloud boundaries.
And identity management across multiple
clouds
is handled differently for each cloud.
So you've got to come up with a strategy
or come up with a common,
access control, software stack
that can handle multiple clouds.
That's
probably your best way to go with that.
All right.
Let's take a look
at an architectural diagram that shows how
this is all working.
I got in this case three clouds,
a private cloud and two public clouds.
Right.
I can set up these partitions
in my, distributed file system.
And through some of the policies,
I can try and make sure that
I have locality set there
for compliance issues or cost issues.
So now when I access my distributed
file system, it will route my request
to the appropriate location
where where that information is.
Now, ideally, you'll have a better idea
of where things are so that you're
not moving data out of the cloud,
where the cost can be prohibitive.
So be smart
about how you're doing these things.
And like I said,
some of the more modern, DfES systems,
you can build those policies in there
and it will say,
maybe you need to move your application
to this cloud where the data is, and
some of them are looking at integrating
into the container
ecosystem for that.
All right.
Let's look at some of those challenges.
Metadata management and complexity.
Across multiple clouds can be difficult
if you're doing it yourself.
Remember there's a centralized
where it's easier to manage
that or distributed right distributed.
Now I've got replication
between, of these, metadata.
A lot of times
they don't use a fully distributed
copy of all the metadata
about a federated system
where it can pass data
between the different metadata servers
and which ends up being, less,
data movement,
but more complexity in managing the data.
You can run into
inconsistencies between the metadata
models, which can cause you some problems.
So you've got to
look at what your trade offs are.
And, the amount of data
that you're moving through these systems
or is it more static.
These all have a play into things.
Also,
understanding your latency and bandwidth
impact on application
responsiveness is critical
because data has become so large
and data gravity being, a big issue here
where your day data is
how big it is, can have a big,
play on where you actually want
to run your applications.
There are some new techniques out there,
a collaborative, scheduling algorithms
between your data, application
or your data, storage management systems
and your container
ecosystems, can have an interesting play.
And these collaborative schedulers
are starting to emerge today
so that it will either
determine whether I'm going to move data
or an application to where the data is.
So interesting
things that are starting to bubble up.
There can be some operational difficulties
when deploying
and managing these systems
across multiple clouds,
because the clouds have different
monitoring systems and things like that.
So you define your monitoring
and your control plane on
this is critical to make this happen.
If you're standing them up
individually with native things,
it can be kind of a nightmare to manage.
So, take a look at that.
And don't forget egress costs.
I can't mention that enough.
It can really bite you, really hard
because you a lot of times,
you may not even know
you're moving data out of the cloud.
So best practices
use TFS solutions
that support multi-cloud and cloud
native chef radar.
NetApp is is one
hammer space is another one.
Macromedia.
There's lots of them
that are starting to emerge out there.
Make sure that you're using any,
intelligent client side
caching that you can that will increase
or decrease, latency problems
and increase efficiency in, cost.
Right.
Also design your replication policies
so that if some thing does go down that
you're not stuck with partial data, right?
So don't replicate. I've seen this happen.
Don't replicate partitions
in the same region or in the same cloud.
Because if that region goes
down, your host right.
And then also make sure that you're
aggregating all your observability data
into a central place
so that you can see how your whole DFS
is actually, being managed and working,
and then automate
scaling of DfES metadata and data services
beyond, beyond just the workload,
that you can actually scale up
these services as they're needed.
A lot of them have the ability
to auto scale, but you need to feed them
the right information
that can be based off of the workloads
that have been scheduled
or their performance.
They should all be based off
of their SLA, SLOs and and slice.
All right.
Observability.
Have I mentioned that before? Yes.
Observability is key here.
This is where your slices come in your,
your service level indicators.
What are you observing.
And then what are your objectives
that you need to meet.
This is where observability
and those are kind of meshed together
so that I can auto scale things.
I can see when nodes have gone down,
which builds into that auto scaling.
I absolutely need to tie this into
the auto scaling mechanisms of the DFS.
If they don't have a built in, then you
need to do something about that, right?
You need to be able to handle
when something goes down,
or if I'm getting a flood of,
of requests.
Right.
I can't, create bottlenecks,
by not having the ability to auto scale
and then don't forget, security,
especially as we have security across
multiple clouds, you're
going to have to be able to handle,
their different IEM systems.
And how are you going to deal with
that? Right.
Some people go, well,
maybe I just shouldn't do multi-cloud.
Well,
maybe you should because of reliability.
You just need to have a tool
that can handle.
And there's lots of great tools out there
now that can talk to the different,
security systems and, identity
systems of the different clouds
run off of one identity.
So, take a look at that.
All right.
There are some great, tools out there.
We've already mentioned self cluster HDFs
and some cloud native integrations
like Amazon, EFS, integrated
with Lambda functions and things
like that, with multiple regions.
Now remember, if you choose a cloud native
distributed file system,
it runs in that cloud and that's it.
So make sure you at least
you're running multiple regions.
But we have seen multiple regions go down
in individual cloud service providers
because of the software patches
that have brought several regions down.
So if you want something highly resilient,
I suggest using a more generic tool
and spanning across
multiple, cloud service providers.
And there's lots of there's
lots of options out there for that.
So back to a big system diagram.
I've got three regions here.
I've got an on on prem, I've got one
cloud and another, public cloud
that are out there.
If you notice,
these distributed
file system architectures
look the same as data
partition architectures because they are
right.
They happen to be an instance of them.
So if you're really interested
in doing file system based type stuff,
there are lots of options
out there, open source
and commercial options
that you can leverage.
So distributed
file systems,
we see them all over the place.
Take advantage of them
but understand what they do.
Especially you got to watch out
for security egress, cost, latency,
all these things, have, a play here
that you've got to understand.
If you're dropping a cluster,
cluster across multiple
clouds,
be ready for some egress costs, right?
Especially if you just have one big volume
with data bricks all over the place
you're going to you're going to take some,
major hit in egress costs
as the, as their,
as the individual nodes
are syncing partitions across
all the nodes, you're going to move data
and you won't even know that
you're doing it.
So be careful.
These things make sure you understand
the underlying architecture, how they work
and what the impact
will be on your architecture.